[MUSIC PLAYING]
SPEAKER 1: All right, this is
CS50, and this is, sadly, the end,
where we wrap up the semester and take
a look back at the past several weeks,
give you a look at what's ahead
in the next several weeks,
and then really the next several
years, how you can sort of go on,
beyond CS50, with the proverbial
training wheels now completely off.
And so that even without things
like CS50 IDE, and Check 50,
and Help 50, and other
such tools, you actually
feel like you can apply all of these
lessons learned, and all of these tools
you've experienced in CS50 to your
own Macs and PCs in the real world.
But I thought it would be perhaps
helpful or reassuring, especially
on the heels of so many problems sets,
some of them especially challenging,
and a recent quiz here on campus, to
just think back at this tenant here.
And we do mean this.
And realize if you're a
little uneasy as to what
remains in store for
the next few weeks, that
what ultimately matters in
this course is not so much
where you end up relative
to your classmates,
but where you end up in week 10,
which is today, relative to yourself
in week zero, some 10 weeks ago.
So that was just a bold claim,
a pie in the sky back then.
But you've made it to this now
finish line, where all that remains
is that one final milestone,
where there's no specification.
You're not told what to do, but you
get to design and implement yourself.
And consider too, over
the past several weeks,
odds are many of you never really felt
like you got your footing, like ever.
Just as you started to grasp something,
we sort of pulled the rug out
from under you, or kind of asked you
to take another step up cognitively,
and actually understand something new.
Well, that's very much
the design of this.
I was trying to think
of metaphors yesterday.
And if you're into like weight
lifting or such, which I'm not,
I suppose the analog
here might be you're
sort of doing your weight
lifting and someone
keeps putting more and more weight on
the thing as you get better and better.
And so you never
actually necessarily feel
like you're making progress,
because it never gets any easier.
But that's just because the
weight on either end is,
so I'm told, is getting
added to and added to.
And I do mean that more
academically here too,
is that with every
passing week, we start
to hope that you were reasonably
comfortable with what was in the past,
so that we could lead you
further along in that journey.
And perhaps most stark is the fact
that 10 weeks ago, many of you
probably found this difficult, right?
It's probably not all that distant
a memory how many minutes, or hours,
or a few days that it actually took
just to get Mario, so to speak--
and Mario's not even in the picture--
to just ascend this kind of
pyramid by using hashtags.
And honestly, just a
week ago, did you all
build this, CS50 finance, which
had a back end implemented
in Python, generating
HTML and CSS dynamically,
that was talking to a
front end, that itself
was built with client-side languages,
like HTML, and CSS, and JavaScript,
talking meanwhile to an API, via HTTP,
that brought in data from a third party
source.
Like, that's where you now are.
And so even if you don't feel 100%
like you could build this from scratch,
and that's fine, indeed what many
students do for their final project is
start with something like P Set 8, tear
out all the finance specific stuff,
and then start to add their
own thoughts, and ideas,
and their own code, notice
just what the Delta truly is.
And that's what we mean by that
Delta between week zero and week 10.
I received, just this past
week, actually, an email
from one of your
classmates, who I thought
was wonderfully reflective on what
their experience had been like.
And quite consistent with this idea of
not quite ever getting their footing,
wrote this, "Besides
learning the new material,
I felt that I started to be
more comfortable with being
uncomfortable and being OK with
working towards building a skill,
rather than getting the right answer."
This is the kind of quote
that you kind of see
in like a Harvard brochure or whatnot,
but it's like, it really is true,
this idea of being comfortable being
uncomfortable is very much the case.
And honestly, you're never really going
to get your footing in this world.
Because honestly, everything we
just taught this past semester
is going to evolve, starting
tomorrow, and in the years to come.
But hopefully, what
we've done in the class,
by choosing certain languages, some
of the most foundational, like C,
and SQL, and now Python, even as
those languages evolve themselves,
or become less used, the
principles of memory management,
and data structures, and tradeoffs,
and abstraction, and encapsulation, all
of those principles,
those aren't going away.
And that's the advantage, I think, of
starting from the so-called ground up.
It wasn't that long ago we were
talking about zeros and ones.
So you're not just
software engineers, you're
computer scientists, or
budding computer scientists,
because you have those
mental models that
can then be applied to any new
technologies or domains that
are down the road.
And if it's reassuring
too, even I feel this way.
Like, I don't feel like I've mastered
CS50 or all of the material therein.
I kind of feel like
that graph that we drew,
that was that green
curved line, where like,
fortunately, I'm always
making some forward progress,
but I'm never actually
reaching the peak of anything,
because there's always
something new to learn.
And it's scary, too.
And, in fact, the most
relevant instance of being
comfortable being uncomfortable,
or maybe if in my case,
being uncomfortable being
uncomfortable, was just a few years ago.
For many years, CS50 had used a language
called PHP for the web programming
portion of the course.
And eventually, we as the staff,
decided it's time to transition
to Python, which has
a number of upsides.
Among them, the applicability
in the real world.
It can be used more
effectively for command line
programs, data science, data analytics,
and it just felt like it was time.
The one to catch was
I didn't know Python.
And so this sounded like a wonderful
idea, sort of philosophically,
that summer, yes, we shall
teach Python this fall.
Then October came
around, and I realized,
oh, Python's coming up in a week or
two, we should probably, we, meaning I,
should probably go learn Python.
And so that entire
semester, was I learning,
and we're repaving the road as we went.
And I swear, if you look back at the
videos from just a few years ago,
the Python lecture was like the
longest lecture ever we have.
Because I was so damn determined to
prove to everyone that I knew Python
by that point in the semester.
So perhaps overcompensating
a little bit.
But this is just to
reassure that none of us
even the smartest of your
teaching fellows and CAs, whom
you interacted with this year,
and myself, like none of us
ever stop learning or stop being a
little uncomfortable with this stuff.
So even if you feel like, wow, I didn't
quite absorb everything this semester,
you weren't ever going to,
because we never did either.
So take that to heart if you would.
Before we forge ahead-- oh, in
fact, I thought I'd mentioned to,
don't aspire to build this,
for instance, mirrored
backgrounds kind of went out of
vogue a long, long, long time ago.
But this was the first example of
me building something, or trying
to solve a problem, that
I had no idea how to do.
CS50 at the time did not
teach web programming.
CS51 at the time did not
teach web programming,
did not teach Perl, or CSV
files, or the kind of ingredients
I needed to build this, or
even HTML or CSS for that--
actually, there was no CSS
at that time, or even HTML.
And so for me, too, this
was an example of being
comfortable being uncomfortable, just
volunteering I will build the Frosh I
Am's website, and then
turning to my roommate,
and saying, how am I going to
build the Frosh I Am's website,
and just getting
comfortable with that idea.
You'll figure it out.
And honestly, the key secret
is to just surround yourself
by really smart, smarter people,
who know way more than you,
who are more comfortable than you,
so you can stand on their shoulders
and learn from them along the way.
And indeed, allow me to thank,
before we forge ahead, just a few
of the folks that you've
either seen or not seen,
especially those behind
the scenes here today,
Mike, and Luke, and Jose, and
Tom, who, with media services,
have helped us with all of this
amazing stuff over the past year.
CS50's production team, Dan and Tara,
and Ian, and Andrew, a couple of whom
are new this year.
And I know they were really
thrown into the fire.
You see one of them too, Max, the guy
who's creepily got a camera on his head
today here-- oh, OK, who
doesn't at the moment--
on our production team as
well, all helped capture this.
And you'll see too, even this world,
of videos influenced by software,
this other camera here, that's just
robotically been going back and forth,
left to right all semester, controlled
essentially by a PS4 controller,
via software and via a
Wi-Fi connection thereto.
So thank you to the team for making
possible so many of the experiences you
all have had here online.
And of course, there's
a whole bigger team
teaching the class, the CAs,
and the TFs, our preceptors,
and the heads of the class, without
whom I certainly could not do this.
These are all of their
names there, sandwiched in.
And perhaps if we could,
and we'll let them
know by playing the video
for them, such a round
of applause that they got here at
lecture is thanks for their time
with us this year.
If we could.
[APPLAUSE]
In particular, you might
have noticed the notes
that are on the course's
website, usually a couple of days
after the lecture.
And this is all thanks
to a former teaching
fellow, Cheng Gong, who graduated a
few years ago in computer science,
and has wonderfully continue to
watch the course's videos, just
a few hours, typically, after
they air, so as to provide you
with a canonical set of notes,
so that you're not yourselves,
heads down, scribbling everything down.
Cheng, therefore, is going to be hearing
and listening to these very words.
And therefore, I've been told to say
just what a wonderful person Chang
Gong is, and how we couldn't do
the course so well without him,
and we really forever appreciate
all of his contributions to CS50,
and he would make a wonderful addition
to any tech company out there.
So, thank you.
Thank you to Chang, as well.
[APPLAUSE]
And allow me to call
out a couple of folks
in particular, two of our undergrads,
who among the most involved
in the course, behind the scenes
and in front of the scenes.
One of whom is in the process of
translating the course into Spanish
with us, so that we can make it
available not only to students here,
but also natively to folks
elsewhere in the world for whom
English is a second, or
not even, a third language.
And therefore, the English
aspects of the class despite,
its being open courseware, are
just an unnecessary hurdle,
in terms of the software, and
the content, and so forth.
And so, in fact, I thought
I'd give you a glimpse
of what CS50's own Veronica has
been doing over the past few months.
For instance, this is what
awaits students online soon,
as they, themselves, tackle, just as the
Myla helped us here in English, Mario,
for instance.
VERONICA: [SPEAKING SPANISH]
SPEAKER 1: My thanks to other folks
behind the scenes, some of whom
you might have met, Aaron, and Greg,
and Doug, and then one other member
of the course's heads, who sadly,
will be graduating this coming spring.
Brian Yu literally wandered
into my office a few years ago.
And we got to chatting
about whether he could get
involved in some form in the course.
And here now, three or so years
later, he spent January's with us,
summers here with us, and
pretty much runs the show now.
And honestly, of all of the head
teaching fellows we've had, all of them
are amazing, but there really is
something special about Brian Yu.
And honestly, in a word,
he is extraordinary.
And what I thought we'd do
is, as thanks to the staff,
and as an invitation to you all, to
consider applying to join us as a TF,
as a CA, as a photographer, as
a producer, any number of hats
that the team here wears, we filmed in
advance, thanks to CS50's production
team, and thanks CS50's own
Connor Doyle, and undergrad,
put together the following film that
Brian has beautifully introduced us to.
And then we'll take a quick look
back at some of our volunteers
who have appeared here in lectures
past on stage, CS50 Puzzle Day
lunches, and more, as a bit of
reflection on where you've all
come this past year.
If we could dim the lights again.
[PIANO MUSIC]
[MUSIC PLAYING]
(SINGING) And it's an open door.
And off [INAUDIBLE]
[MUSIC PLAYING]
(SINGING) Help me out, let me down.
I could learn from you,
I could learn from you.
Help me out, let me down.
So if we could, a round of
applause again for the staff.
[APPLAUSE]
So let's take a quick
look back then at what
it meant to be 10 weeks ago, when we
tore, and I was actually just thinking,
we probably should have added the meme
clip to that part of the video here,
we tore this phone book in
half and began our discussion
of computational thinking
and all things thereafter.
And what we hope to do
with this quick look,
is to just remind you just
how far, truly, you've come,
and to sort of remind how
hopefully a number of these topics
have all coincided and intermingled.
So this was computer science, right?
In week zero, we proposed this black
box, that we revealed to be algorithms.
And we had inputs and outputs.
We needed to represent those
inputs and outputs, and thus
were it was born zeros,
and ones, and binary.
And from there, did we talk
about higher level abstractions,
talking about how you might have decimal
or letters of the alphabet, ASCII
and Unicode, the number 65,
representing the same there,
the same pattern of bits might
represents something like a dot,
or a pixel of yellow.
If you have a whole bunch
of those dots or pixels,
you might have a crying face of joy.
And if you might have
multiple images like that,
you might have animojis
or videos, more generally,
which are just yet another
abstraction on top of that.
And so, as you go out into the
real world now, after CS50,
and see pretty fancy and
newfangled technologies,
just start to critique
them in your mind.
And consider, well, I know
how this feature is done,
and I know how that feature
implements that feature.
Odds are, you can reverse
engineer in your mind how many
of today's technologies
work, just by building
backwards to those lower levels.
We then introduced
pseudo-codes, so we could
talk about what it meant
to express yourself
more carefully, more methodically.
And we introduced loops, and
conditions, and variables,
and other such tenants,
that we then translated,
eventually to another language.
And we also talked not about
correctness, but about efficiency.
So that you have a mental model of just
how good your code, or your algorithm,
or your thought ultimately is.
And then was introduced
Scratch, so that you
had a way, albeit
graphically, to express
all of these various components,
by programming Scratch up and down,
and left and right.
Of course, things got pretty
scary, or ugly, pretty quickly.
We then transitioned to C, when all of
a sudden, the simplest of "Hello world,"
started to look like that.
Odds are, that first week, if
you'd never seen any programming
language before, let alone
C, most of those lines
did not look familiar, except
for perhaps the "Hello world,"
but even that thing was followed
by some random backslash n.
And all of that have we, hopefully,
teased apart over the past many weeks.
That, of course, gets compiled
down to zeros and ones,
which the computer only understands.
And thankfully, we humans
live in an age where
we don't need to worry about
that level, or relatively few
of us do, because we have
abstractions, and libraries,
and other developments on top.
In week two, did we then introduce
other aspects of programming,
and functions, and return
values, and the like.
And we also talked about what's
really going on underneath the hood.
Code, like this here, for
instance, gets compiled often
into multiple files, CS50s,
standard iOS and your own code,
and then they all get linked together.
But there too, that's what
you're getting for free,
so to speak, by running a
compiler like Clang, albeit again
and again, whenever you
make a change to your code.
We introduced the notion of
memory, a little chip that
might be in your computer.
And if we zoom in on
that, it really is just
this beautiful, simple canvas
of bytes, top to bottom,
left to right, that you can
do anything you want with.
Like that is it.
Despite all of the seeming
complexity of a computer,
that is the canvas that
you have to work with.
And that was allowing us to do
any number of the data structures
and algorithms on top of it.
For instance, in week three,
we talked about strings.
And strings were very straightforward.
You might not have
heard the word initially
in the context of programming,
but just a sequence of characters,
like a word, a phrase,
a sentence, or such.
And then things got scary
again quickly, when we said,
those are a little bit of a
white lie, and abstraction,
more properly, on top of pointers.
Of course, pointers themselves
got a little scary quickly.
And even in retrospect,
this might still look scary.
And that's fine.
The reality most of you will not
have occasion to program in C again.
The only occasions I have are generally
in September and October of every year,
myself, because in the real world,
I tend not to use this language,
though it does remain super
popular and super commonly used,
especially in hardware based
contexts, where you really
want to squeeze as much performance
as possible out of the hardware,
and you don't necessarily want the
overhead of a higher level language,
like Python.
But what's important is
just those principles.
The fact that you can put things
in memory, you can go there,
you can move them.
That's all this crazy syntax
has been doing for us.
Of course, it didn't end well
for Binky, when you abused this.
And indeed a lot of today's
programming errors, even
ones that are still with us today,
reduce to misusing or accidentally
touching memory that you should not.
But once you have that primitive,
this ability to stitch things together
in memory, then you can start
to build things in software.
We introduced Structs, in C, which allow
us to come up with our own custom data
types that have multiple
things inside of them.
And once you have that,
if one of those things
is itself a pointer
to something else, you
can kind of string things
together in memory,
thereby giving you access to linked
lists, which solve problems when
it comes to the limitations of arrays.
And you can do even fancier things like
hash tables, that might conceptually
and pictorial look like
this, or even the crazier
tri, which theoretically,
is even more efficient,
it just takes up so much more space.
But that's it.
With pointers, all you're doing
is stitching these data structures
together.
And even though most languages on top
of C, like Python, and Java, and PHP,
and Ruby, don't have
pointers per se, they
have the idea of addresses
or references still.
So the concept is there, they've
just made it a little easier
not to shoot yourself in the foot by
making mistakes and getting things
like seg fault. The compilers
and the interpreters
are increasingly getting good at helping
you protect yourself from human error.
And then, thereafter, we began to
transition, felt like a long time in C,
but we began to talk about HTTP,
and virtual envelopes and messages,
just going from point A to point B.
And among those things were headers.
And you'll recall, perhaps
among the more amusing headers,
was this one, bought some years ago.
If you use a browser or if you use
Curl, like a program at the command
line, and the IDE, or your Mac or
PC, and you actually request this,
what was the status code that came back?
Anyone recall?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
SPEAKER 1: Wasn't 200, wasn't 404.
SPEAKER 1: Yeah, it was
like permanently redirected.
I think 301 or 302 came back,
and where did it lead to?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
SPEAKER 1: Yale University.
So that was nice and fun.
Of course, they bought
HarvardSucks.org some time ago.
And for those unfamiliar,
this weekend is,
of course, the Harvard-Yale football
game, here in Cambridge this year.
So as clever as Yale has been for
like a decade of paying annually
for, or rather as clever as we
have been, whoever the alum,
is paying for a decade
for Safetyschool.org
redirecting to Yale.edu, unfortunately,
HarvardSucks.org also lives on.
In fact, there's a whole
wonderful back story there,
that was about 12-plus years ago now.
Where some enterprising students
at Yale kind of really got us.
Have folks seen or heard this story?
So we really embarrassed
ourselves some years ago.
And it will all boil down to some
very enterprising Yale students
using a little bit of software
and a computer program
to create an actual bitmap, like
a grid of pixels using humans.
The problem was that those humans
were us, on the Harvard side,
in the Harvard stadium.
Because we essentially created a bitmap
message, thanks to their cleverness.
So I thought we'd dim the lights
and for about three minutes,
look at just how bad they got us.
Now to be fair, we got them for like
12 years, or 19 years of football
thereafter, though they have been
winning the past couple of years.
So we can't really talk about this now.
So without further ado, let's dim
the lights and pull this look up too.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
- We're headed up to Boston,
checking out the stadium for a prank.
- A few years ago, I was
at a math conference.
And I was sitting around
at the table at dinner,
with a few other mathematicians.
And one of them went
to Harvard, and started
telling the story of this amazing
prank that was against Harvard.
And at that point, I
felt I had to interrupt,
and said, well, actually I can
tell you a lot more about that.
- OK.
- The idea was perfected in a dorm room.
- We came up with the idea,
actually, to prank them
with signs at the football game.
We threw some ideas out there as
far as what the signs would say.
We eventually settled on "We Suck."
and my immediate reaction
was, no, this will never work.
However, the problem solver in me
started thinking, well, maybe we
can make this work.
- The problem, they had to infiltrate
Harvard stadium without getting caught,
sneak in 1,800 placards, distribute
them to unsuspecting Harvard fans,
and then convince those
fans to prank themselves.
- That's great.
- We thought about basically every
possible thing that could go wrong
and tried to come up
with a solution for it.
- And then you put
two guys on top of it.
- They made fake Harvard IDs and fake
backstories, fake placard designs,
and a 28-member fake pep squad.
On November 20th, 2004,
the fake Harvard students
smuggled the placards into the game.
- What do you think of Yale, sir?
- They suck.
- It's not going to say
something like Yale sucks, is it?
- It says go Harvard.
- But then, trouble.
- What houses are you guys in?
- That's not a real house.
- Ho-fo?
- Yeah.
- You guys aren't from Harvard, are you?
- Can I see your Harvard ID because I
really think you guys are from Yale.
- I just showed him
the front of this ID,
and all the sudden, he just ran
away, and he felt so embarrassed.
- Having escaped one confrontation,
they couldn't risk another.
It was time.
- This just looks like a total mess.
- We have absolutely no idea
if this is going to work.
- Look at them, they have the paper.
It's actually going to happen.
I can't [BEEP] believe this.
- What was once a
prank, became a legend.
- We did it.
- And immediately, we started
hearing chants from the other side.
You suck.
- You suck, you suck, you suck.
- And I think it was at that point in
time that we knew we had pulled it off.
- One more time.
- There it goes again.
- I really think it
didn't matter that Harvard
won, because of the prank for a
lot of Yale students and alumni,
we definitely won that year.
[END PLAYBACK]
SPEAKER 1: So there you go problem
solving at Harvard, Yale as well.
All right, the bar has been set.
So thereafter, let's try to
somehow make this more academic
again, so thereafter, did we transition
from looking at the principles of HTTP,
and the envelopes with
which you can send messages,
and actually introduced
a language with which
we can create user interfaces
and things far more interesting
than terminal windows alone.
Of course, there was a connection
even to the material past,
because underneath the
hood, what your browser is
doing is reading that HTML,
top to bottom, left to right,
and building really a
tree structure in memory,
that you can then manipulate using
JavaScript, yet another language.
And then in week six, did
we tragically point out
that all that complexity we'd
wrestled with just a few weeks ago,
trying to build a linked list with null
at the end and pointers throughout,
actually reduces to just this in
Python, just a single line of code.
And then this amazing data
structure that theoretically
has constant time access
and dynamic growth,
because you can chain
everything off of it.
You just have to write a lot of code
to do all the memory management,
is just this in Python.
But underneath the hood,
that is what Python is doing.
In fact, a lot of the Python
interpreter, the program called Python,
is itself written in C. And so
someone, just thankfully not you,
has had to write all
of that functionality.
But Python itself is
just an abstraction.
These functions are abstractions on
top of these lower level implementation
details.
And that should really become
part of your vocabulary,
distinguishing between design,
and abstractions, and lower level
implementation details,
all of which are important,
but they don't all need to
be at the tip of your mind
when you're thinking about
how to solve a problem.
You can solve problems at this level.
And then lower down into
the implementation details.
So after that, we tried to
tie everything together.
And we looked more generally
at web programming.
We just looked at one paradigm of
web programming, the MVC model,
so to speak.
There are dozens,
probably more these days,
all of them with fancy
confusing acronyms.
But it's just different
ways to solve problem.
Because we humans,
with each passing year,
realize that, hey, I, in my
company, and you, in your company,
and you, in your dorm, we're all
trying to solve similar ideas.
We're all trying to make an app.
We're all trying to make a website.
And we're all reinventing wheels.
And so new frameworks are invented,
and new methodologies, and people
start sharing.
And the world starts to collaborate
by way of open source tools,
that we, ourselves, have used, like
Flask being one such example thereof,
jQuery a little bit, Bootstrap
as well, all of which
allow us to sort of solve
problems collectively
and get real, more interesting work
done without having to deal with all
of those implementation details.
And then lastly, did we
introduce one last language, SQL,
which gave us all the
more of a back end, where
we can store stuff, a
lot more stuff, and a lot
more easily than we
could with CSVs alone.
And if you like this world of
statistics, and data science,
and the like, or if you're going
back to the world of the humanities,
or medicine, or any number of fields,
where there's just lots of words,
lots of books, lots of texts,
lots of data, ultimately, SQL,
and all of these languages can be
used to help you answer questions
that you might have in those domains.
So from there, where do we go?
So after Thanksgiving break here
in Cambridge is the CS50 hackathon.
It will begin at 7:00 PM in the
evening, and it will end at 7:00 AM
the next night.
And it's meant to be one of those
uniquely collegiate experiences, where
you have alongside you all of
your friends and classmates,
and all of the course's staff into
the night, working on final projects.
An opportunity to be productive.
An opportunity far enough away from
the deadline to feel good about it
and to take breaks, and to
have dinner with us at 9:00 PM,
to have second dinner
with us around 1:00 AM.
And then if you're
still awake, around 5:00
AM we charter some Harvard
shuttles, and take ourselves
to IHOP for breakfast as well.
But you're welcome to go to
sleep at any point in between.
Just to give you a
sense of what it's like.
On arrival, the students
from both Harvard and Yale
ascend the stairs, joining the staff
for the evening of programming.
We have reserved the entire
space above the Innovation Lab
across the river at
HBS, where everyone will
be able to tuck themselves away
into a corner with their partners,
or with their friends,
or classmates more
generally, and just work throughout
the night on their final projects.
There's a photo booth,
and a Myla as well,
as well as other members of the staff.
There are therapy dogs in some years,
if you'd like to take a little break
and meet such puppies as these.
And then, of course,
at 5:00 AM, is IHOP.
And this is Maria
Zlatkova, now at Facebook,
greeting us at last year's breakfast.
And then the CS50 fair.
On both campuses is this event.
An opportunity for
all of you to show off
just what you accomplish
this semester, truly meant
to be the capstone of what you've
done, not exhibiting your own problems
sets that you were told how to build,
but your own project that you yourself
decided how to.
We'll invite the entire campus,
the faculty, students, and staff
from across campus.
Usually it's about 2,000-plus people.
We'll be in the beautifully
renovated Smith Center this year,
right in Harvard Square.
So we expect to have quite a few
passers by and tourists as well.
It's always coupled with
a fabulous raffle, whereby
you'll all be given, as student
presenters, little smiley face
stickers or such.
Anyone who chats you up and
asks you about your project
and for a quick demo on
your laptop or phone,
you'll be able to hand them a
sticker and be eligible, therefore,
for fabulous prizes.
Along the way though, there'll
be popcorn, and snacks,
and music, and more.
Some of our alumni from
industry to talk to you
about the real world, and summer time,
and full-time opportunities as well.
And what you'll see is a space
that looks, and feels, and sounds,
rather like this, with
folks just mingling around,
really proud and happy to see what it
is that you and your friends pulled off.
With popcorn in attendance, stress balls
in attendance, and staff, and students
alike, hopefully delighting
in what it is that you did.
Everyone will end the semester
with a I took CS50 t-shirt.
Hopefully, this is something
you two will wear proud.
In fact, this truly is
where I got my start.
1996, CS50 changed my life.
And, in fact-- in fact,
here, is indeed proof
of just how proud I am to have actually
gotten my way through this course
so long ago, when I, myself, had not had
the nerve freshman year even to shop.
So hopefully, you feel yourselves
a member of that community as well.
So of course, we thought we'd give you
a sense of what the next few weeks might
be like, especially if you don't
necessarily budget your time properly.
A few years ago, we used
before the CS50 IDE,
the software called
CS59 Appliance, which
was like a downloadable version
of it for your Mac and PC.
It tended to be a little slower,
and you'll see an allusion to that.
But this video produced by CS50's
production team, and particularly
Dan Coffee, was CS50's first
experimentation with puppetry.
And you'll see that we
tell the story by proxy
of a CS50 student working on their final
project, just as the deadline nears.
And so if we could dim
the lights, this will
be our last of the videos for today
before we now look ahead at the years
after.
[PHONE RINGING]
[MUSIC PLAYING
- "MISSION IMPOSSIBLE"]
So our thanks to Dan Coffee
and the team for producing that
as well, if we could.
[APPLAUSE]
That is indeed exactly
how deadlines work.
Every time we have a deadline, I--
So life after 50.
So the training wheels are off,
you can keep the rubber duck
and have someone to talk to
as you wrestle with problems.
But the CS50 IDE, while
you can keep using it,
it's not something you, odds are, going
to use in the real world for very long.
And there really is no check 50
and help 50 in the real world,
though there are lots of humans.
They are not called TFs anymore,
they're called friends and colleagues.
But you can lean on those folks as well.
And what we thought we'd
give you is some list
of suggestions for next steps, so that
you feel like there's offboarding.
And honestly, some of
this will happen naturally
as you tackle your final
projects, depending on the nature.
And if you take another class, or CS50
beyond this winter, or you experience
these things yourselves, but we
thought we'd at least give you
some links in today's
slides, so that you
have something to tinker with over
Thanksgiving, or winter break,
or beyond.
So CS50 IDE is meant to be
representative of a very
common programming environment.
It happens to be web based, it
happens to be in our domain name.
But this idea of having a
file browser of some sort,
and tabs where you write
code, and a terminal window
with which you interact,
incredibly, incredibly, common,
whether it's in the cloud, or
more commonly for real world
software developers on
your own Mac or your PC.
Frankly, some years from now, this will
probably be the way it is, none of us
use our Mac, PCs per se,
everything probably is remotely.
So odds are, at some point in the
future, we'll come full circle.
But for now, it's quite
common to replicate this kind
of setup on your own Mac or PC.
So how do you go about having a command
line, which hopefully you've gleaned,
while frustrating, is more
powerful than only having
menus and icons available
to you that someone else,
like a company, like Microsoft
or Apple has given you.
Well, in both Macs and PCs,
can you install the same tools
that we used this
semester, Clang, and Make,
and you get CD, and LS, and
[? Miktor, ?] and all of those commands
on both Mac OS or Windows.
And the starting points can be here.
Both of those provide their own sort
of terminal windows, and the software
therein.
You can just install via
those two starting points.
Now what about Git?
You've seen or heard
about Git, even though we
don't use it hands on in the class.
Odds are you will use this in higher
level CS courses, if you take it.
It's one of the most
popular programs with which
to save versions of your software.
Now you may have noticed the CS50
IDE does this automatically for you.
You can go to File, Revision
History, and you can kind of
go back and forth in time.
And that's great and wonderfully useful,
but it doesn't really lend itself
to collaborating with others.
And so, if you're working with
partners for the final project,
in the simplest form, you
can just have one of you
share your CS50 IDE with
the other user names.
And you'll all just
share the same account.
And that's fine.
But it gets a little
annoying and complicated
if you're both trying
to edit the same files,
you're not necessarily talking to one
another, or you're in different rooms.
Like, at some point you
want to have good workflows.
And so via this URL here, does Brian
introduce you to Git, a command line
tool that's super, super, super
popular these days, that lets
you save versions of your code.
So you no longer call it
Mario 1.C, and Mario 2.C,
and Mario 3 AM.C and the like.
You actually call it Mario.C.
But you let Git take care of
time-stamping it and versioning it
for you.
And Git allows you to share
your code in the cloud.
What we use GitHub for is for,
of course, submissions, and such,
and for commenting.
But more generally, it's
used for just storing
code and sharing with other people.
So what you'll do with
Git is literally Git
push it to a service like a
GitHub, or GitLabs, or others.
Where someone else can then Git
pull it onto their own Mac or PC.
And, therefore, you're sharing files.
You don't email.
You don't Dropbox, or the like.
You actually use a
standardized software tool.
You can install it
via these instructions
here, if you don't have it already.
And more usefully too, can you
sign up for free repositories
GitHub.com, you already have an account.
Since you have a student
ID, you can go to this URL
here and tell them you're a student
at Harvard, or Yale, or beyond.
And then say, can I please
have free private repos,
so you can keep your own personal
or school projects private,
without needing access to
CS50's own organization.
So what do you write code in?
So, there's bunches
of editors these days.
Among the most popular
is a tools that's called
Atom, which is an open
source text editor that
has lots and lots of plug-ins.
This is like the tabbed
windows for writing code.
It does syntax, highlighting,
and so much more,
so that your code is easy to
edit, and it looks pretty wild
you're working on it, and
just makes life pretty easy.
Also super popular these days is
VS Code or Visual Studio Code.
They are functionally
pretty much equivalent.
You can ask your teaching fellows
or friends which you prefer,
or just try them both.
They are free, and there's
dozens of other options.
These two just currently have
a lot of momentum in industry.
Within the terminal window, though, is
what a lot of CS students would use,
something called Vim.
And there's alternatives there,
called [? Emax ?] and a few others.
But Vim is actually what I grew up
on, and still to this day tend to use.
I tend not to use a GUI.
I just use a bigger terminal window
with lots and lots of code inside of it.
And Vim is more of a
command line tool, where
you have to memorize
keyboard shortcuts more so,
but it's also more
powerful in the same way
a terminal window tends to be as well.
So whatever you are most
comfortable with is fine.
So suppose you want to post a
website, like your own personal home
page, your resume, an artistic
portfolio, or whatnot,
where do you even begin?
You can certainly make it on
your Mac or PC in an HTML file,
but no one in the world can access it.
You can put it in CS50
IDE, but that goes
to sleep eventually,
when you're not using it,
which makes it hard for people on
the internet to visited at any hour.
But fortunately, there's so
many free services out there,
at least if you have modest usage.
If you're trying to
build a business, odds
are you're going to pay someone
for the bandwidth, and the support,
and so forth.
But if you just have a home page, where
you're getting dozens, hundreds, maybe
low thousands of visits,
which is probably
likely the case for
personal sites, you can
use something called GitHub Pages, a
free service where you store your HTML
files, JavaScript,
and CSS on GitHub.com,
and they host it for you for free.
Netlify is another free
one too, and dot, dot, dot,
you can Google ad nauseam and find
any number of free such services.
These just tend to be two popular
ones with which I too am familiar.
Hosting a web app, so not a static
website, but something more dynamic,
we'll have instructions that we'll
circulate for this final project
as well, so that you can sort
of graduate from CS50 IDE
and run your final
project, or your website,
or your student group's tool,
or your startup's website
on a third-party service.
Heroku tends to be very popular.
They too have a free tier of service.
So long as your website's not being
hammered by lots and lots of users,
you can use it for free.
You get free access to a database,
something called Post [? Gress, ?]
which we alluded to
earlier in the semester,
using the same data types we discussed.
Wix is another common one too, that very
recently launched support for code, not
just static web sites too.
So these are starting points.
But certainly use Google or the
like to find other options as well.
Then there's infrastructure,
as a service, so to speak.
There's some bigger fish out there,
Amazon, and Microsoft, and Google,
that have cloud-based services.
The learning curve tends to
be a little higher, frankly.
So I would encourage you to maybe
start with the previous examples, which
are businesses built
on top of these layers.
But if you're interested,
absolutely sign up
as a student for any
number of these services,
and they tend to give you
lots of financial credits,
so you can just try things
for free, for like a month,
or a year, or whatnot
to get your feet wet.
It's a wonderfully free
world when you're just
getting started in this space.
And then more general advice.
Read lots.
And I'm sure if you ask
the TFs and CAs, you'll
get an even longer list of sites.
But these tend to be the kinds of
sites I go to if I just kind of want
to stay in the loop on things.
Subscribing to various
sub-Reddits, so to speak,
is compelling, where information, news,
conversations, just get pushed at you.
And honestly, whenever I'm
asked how I kind of stay
in touch with certain things,
I hear things from friends,
I get emails about technologies, I
get curious, and so I poke around.
And these tend to be the places that
I might go, and a lot of tech people
go, to talk about new
trends and technologies.
Or if you're trying to vet something,
should I use x or should I use y,
don't just use Google.
Check out those websites as well.
And then CS50, if you'd
like to stay in touch.
So CS50, not so much here on campus,
but for students around the world,
maintains a number of online
communities, all of which
you're welcome to partake in, answering
questions, or asking questions,
or the like.
And those are just the few
of the current ones now.
Any questions on any or all
of those past or future steps?
Anything at all?
No?
All right.
OK, so we'll adjourn
in just a little bit
time for our tradition of
cake downstairs in the pub.
But we also have one other
tradition, especially now
that you have some 10 weeks
of experience behind you.
For all intents and
purposes, you are all now
qualified as CS50 staff, because,
indeed, at the end of the day,
most of CS50 staff are recent
alumni of the course themselves,
sophomores, juniors, seniors, recent
graduates, students online who
have taken this class, maybe taken
another class in the spring or beyond,
and then joined us as staff.
So realize that even if you're
not feeling more comfortable yet,
or most comfortable, nor
are most of the staff,
and myself included, with
a lot of these things.
And so long as you stay one step ahead
and you know the kinds of resources
to turn to, this is what it really
is about when learning in this world.
And in fact, a very common
mindset, I do know, in the class,
in the problem sets, in
the quiz, is wait a minute,
you didn't teach us this.
And that, odds are, was
quite true quite often.
And I don't just mean
to be rationalizing it.
That was very much by design.
In the real world, that's exactly the
emotion you're hopefully going to feel,
or realistically going
to feel quite often.
And we truly do hope that
among the tools you've gotten,
training wheels and beyond, is to know
where to have the right instincts now
with how to bootstrap yourself, so to
speak, and solve problems, and learn
things on your own.
But we thought we would, in
conclusion put that to the test.
And I think for this, we need--
let's see, we have a bunch of chairs
up here, four student volunteers,
for about to be--
four about to be alumni volunteers.
OK, over here in the
front, yeah, come on down.
Over here, in the front, and three.
And let me try to see about
four, over here, come on down.
All right four, you have four?
Colton's going to join us.
Uh-oh, OK, we'll take five, that's
fine, but you gotta bring a chair.
We'll find a chair somewhere.
Come on down.
And now I need four staff
volunteers, if we could.
Who on the staff might--
Oh, yes, ma'am come on up.
Athena has volunteered.
Oh, Erin, would you like to--
oh, come up.
Yeah, who?
OK, yeah, come on up, Robert.
OK, thank you so much for volunteering.
OK, so-- but the catch is, we
need the staff on their own team.
So let's put the students
here, because you need--
that's OK.
Could you guys go over here?
OK, all five of you-- we have
our student team over here.
And we'll find you one more
chair in just a moment.
Staff, go ahead and take a seat here.
You each have a piece of
paper, a pen, and a microphone.
And why don't we go ahead,
as we get ready to go here--
do you want to each just say
hello and introduce yourself?
ERIN: Hello.
SPEAKER 1: Well, you can tell them.
ERIN: Hello, I'm Erin, one
of the course preceptors.
ISAAC: I'm Isaac, I'm a TF.
ROBERT: I'm Robert, I'm a CA.
ATHENA: And I'm Athena, I'm a TF.
ANDREA: Hi, I'm Andrea,
I'm an alumni, soon.
AVIVA: Hi, I'm Aviva, me too.
JONATHAN: I'm Jonathan.
APRIL: April.
ERIC: I'm Eric.
COLTON: Hi, I Colton,
I'm a technologist.
SPEAKER 1: All right, so what are we
all doing up here, you might wonder.
Well, we have this tradition
of using all of those questions
that you offered for the quiz, recall
in problem set seven, just a couple
of weeks ago, as refreshers.
Now mind you, there is quite
the difference between, I think,
a lot of the questions you offered
up at suggestions for quiz questions.
Many of them were like,
what is two in binary,
or maybe what is three in binary.
And so, that was great.
But we were looking for a
little harder questions.
And we get some of those too.
And so Colton kindly went
through the thousands
of questions that were
submitted just a couple of weeks
ago, to pluck out some of the most
serious, some of the most playful ones.
And I have here them
clustered into categories,
because we have this tradition
of playing our own version, staff
versus students, of Jeopardy.
Now because you all wrote the
questions in the form of questions,
I'm going to read them in the
form of questions and not answers.
So it's more of a quiz show, if
we could, staff versus students.
The first person to raise their
hand, we'll call on first.
We don't have buzzer technology here.
Colton will be our judge, if
you don't mind being the judge.
And we'll do just a few
rounds of single and double,
and on Final Jeopardy, followed by cake.
So in a moment, we'll
show you the categories,
and begin asking the questions.
Do you have any questions of your own?
STUDENT: Are we
answering with questions?
SPEAKER 1: You will be
answering as an answer.
I'll ask the questions, you answer.
So it's not really Jeopardy, but
it just kind of sounds better
if we call it Jeopardy.
OK, so-- and also, also, look at what
we made in HTML to facilitate this.
Let's zoom in.
Here we go, Enhance, whoo-hoo, look
at those HTML tables and links.
OK, so without further ado,
I think before today began,
we decided that the students
had won the coin toss.
Would you like to pick a
category, and then I'll
ask you a question in that category.
STUDENT: Scratch for 1,000.
SPEAKER 1: Scratch-- for $100?
STUDENT: No, there's no $100.
STUDENT: $1,000.
SPEAKER 1: Oh, I heard 1,000.
STUDENT: Yeah, 1,000.
SPEAKER 1: OK, so week--
week zero, week zero, the question
is what institution develop Scratch.
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
SPEAKER 1: Colton?
SPEAKER 1: Whoever
raises their hand first.
COLTON: [INAUDIBLE]
SPEAKER 1: OK, OK, students.
STUDENT: MIT.
SPEAKER 1: MIT is the correct
answer for 1,000 points.
Very nicely done.
OK, if no one's going to clap--
[APPLAUSE]
SPEAKER 1: There we go.
No it's OK.
We have an HTML button for that too.
All right, so students,
you have control.
What would you like?
STUDENT: Scratch for 800.
STUDENT: Yeah, I was--
SPEAKER 1: Scratch for what?
STUDENT: All the Scratch ones.
STUDENT: Scratch for 800.
SPEAKER 1: Scratch for 800, working
our way through the Scratch questions.
OK, what color is the cat?
Students--
STUDENT: Orange.
SPEAKER 1: Orange, OK, now funny
enough, two people asked this question
in P Set 7, and we got two answers--
yellow and orange.
Perhaps by a show of hands-- yellow--
orange.
OK, orange, students get the $800.
Very nicely done.
Students--
STUDENT: We should do something big.
STUDENT: Don't do C.
I'm terrible with C.
STUDENT: Arrays.
STUDENT: No.
STUDENT: Arrays are easy.
STUDENT: Fine.
STUDENT: Fine, arrays.
STUDENT: Arrays for 1,000.
SPEAKER 1: Arrays for 1,000.
So this is from week two for 1,000.
This is going to be--
what is the running time of merge sort?
Staff?
STAFF: End log in.
SPEAKER 1: End log in
is correct for a 1,000.
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
SPEAKER 1: Staff, what would you like.
STAFF: Memory.
SPEAKER 1: Memory for--
STAFF: 1,000.
SPEAKER 1: For a 1,000?
STAFF: Yeah.
SPEAKER 1: OK, for 1,000, what
is the name of the tool you
can run to see if your program--
staff?
STAFF: Valgrind.
SPEAKER 1: If your program has memory
leaks, Valgrind is correct, for 1,000.
STAFF: [INAUDIBLE]
STAFF: That was nice.
SPEAKER 1: Staff for 1,000,
what do you want next?
STAFF: Week Star, what is that?
SPEAKER 1: Oh, week star is the
wild card, so you can get any week.
STAFF: Week Star for 1,000.
SPEAKER 1: Week Star for 1,000.
So I shall choose the category to be--
what is rubber duck debugging?
What is rubber duck debugging?
Students?
STUDENT: I'll answer it.
It's when you read every
line of code to a rubber
duck and to try and find a mistake.
SPEAKER 1: I think that's correct.
Very well done for 1,000.
[APPLAUSE]
All right, I think we have time for
one more question in single Jeopardy.
Students you have control and the lead.
STUDENT: Go for the lowest
possible [INAUDIBLE]..
STUDENT: No, why don't we
try Week for 800, or C for--
STUDENT: For like 200, because
then they can't catch up.
STUDENT: So 200.
STUDENT: Yeah.
SPEAKER 1: Students?
STUDENT: C for 200.
SPEAKER 1: For what?
SPEAKER 1: C for-- whoa, OK.
C for 200 in week one.
Week 1-- your question is going to be--
is C the absolute worst?
Students, for 200?
STUDENT: OK, I think it's not, because--
STUDENT: The person asking
that would say, yes,
so we just have to match their answer.
STUDENT: We have to match their answer?
SPEAKER 1: The correct
answers are right here.
STUDENT: Yes.
SPEAKER 1: No.
This is what I'm told.
STUDENT: Yes.
SPEAKER 1: I hear two yeses and one no.
STUDENT: I stick by my opinion.
STUDENT: Majority wins.
SPEAKER 1: The answer
is yes, it is the worst.
STUDENT: Yes.
SPEAKER 1: For 200.
OK, so we're now moving
on to Double Jeopardy,
where all the dollar values
are doubled and the categories
have changed two later weeks,
still with one wild card.
Students.
STUDENT: Oh, god.
SPEAKER 1: Python for 2,000.
SPEAKER 1: For 2,000.
STUDENT: I'm sorry, I
just made that decision.
STUDENT: Python, 2,000.
SPEAKER 1: What week?
SPEAKER 1: Python for 2,000.
So that's week six.
Python for 2,000, and a question
that a classmate asked was,
what is an animal that you don't want
to find under your pillow that shares
its name with a programming language?
Students.
STUDENT: Python snake.
A python snake.
SPEAKER 1: Python is
correct, yes, for $2,000.
Very nice.
Students, Python 6,000.
SPEAKER 1: Time for just a few
questions before we move on to final.
STUDENT: Oh, let's do, like Web--
do you guys want to do Web--
STUDENT: Sure, Web 2,000.
SPEAKER 1: Web for 2,000,
that was week seven.
And a question here
was, who is your friend?
STUDENT: What?
SPEAKER 1: Students for 2,000.
Oh, did you see Erin first?
Sorry, Colton's the judge.
STAFF: Developer tools?
SPEAKER 1: I'm sorry, that's incorrect.
Yes, students?
STUDENT: Inspect Elements?
STUDENT: Inspect Elements.
SPEAKER 1: Inspect Element,
also incorrect, I'm afraid.
Students, again?
STUDENT: A rubber duck.
SPEAKER 1: A rubber duck is incorrect.
STUDENT: Google.
SPEAKER 1: Google, no.
I think you're negative 8,000 now.
But that's OK, we won't deduct.
We won't deduct, it's fine.
I know that's not how Jeopardy's played.
OK.
STAFF: W3 Schools?
SPEAKER 1: W3 Schools, incorrect.
Students-- What?
STUDENT: David [INAUDIBLE]?
SPEAKER 1: No, not him.
Yeah?
STUDENT: Stack Exchange?
SPEAKER 1: What?
SPEAKER 1: Not Stack Exchange.
The answer is Bootstrap.
OK, moving on.
So time for two more
questions in Double Jeopardy.
The students I think had control, right?
STUDENT: Yeah.
STUDENT: What do you guys want to do?
SPEAKER 1: Staff need
to pull ahead here.
STUDENT: Just like any
for week for 2,000.
STUDENT: Wild card 2,000?
STUDENT: Week [INAUDIBLE] for 2,000.
STUDENT: Wild card, 2,000.
STUDENT: Wild card for 2,000.
Audience, what week shall we give them?
One through seven, 0 through 7.
Four, I heard.
Week four.
Week four-- what is the code for OK?
Staff?
STAFF: 200.
SPEAKER 1: 200 for 2,000.
All right, so staff have control.
We have time for one more question
before we move on to Final Jeopardy.
STAFF: [INAUDIBLE]
STAFF: No, we want to be able
to be in touch with it, right?
Data structures, 1,200.
SPEAKER 1: Data structures for 1,200.
Data structures for 1,200.
And that was, what week was that?
Four, that's week four.
What do you call the
situation when a structure
refers to itself in its definition?
Students?
STUDENT: Recursion.
SPEAKER 1: Recursion is
correct for $1,200, very nice.
OK, so we now go into our last question
of CS50 of staff versus students.
Staff have 4,000, students have 6,200.
You're about to be told the Final
Jeopardy category, at which point
each team needs to commit in writing,
on the sheet of paper in front of them,
with the CS50 pen in front
of them, to a dollar amount,
keeping in mind that you will
either gain or lose this amount.
All right, go ahead
and choose your-- oh,
here we go, the category for Final
Jeopardy is going to be Buggy.
Buggy will be your category.
Any dollar amount.
OK, so, so, here we go.
The question is, they've all
committed to a dollar amount.
OK, I feel like you can
hedge your bets there.
All right, so here we go, Final
Jeopardy, Buggy is the category.
In which state, besides Massachusetts,
does Google sometimes think we reside?
[MUSIC PLAYING - "JEOPARDY THEME SONG"]
All right.
So, I think staff were not in
the lead, or not in the lead,
so we start with you.
Staff, first of all,
how much did you wager?
OK, depending, I think,
on how the question went,
they wagered either
$4,000 or $40, apparently.
STAFF: [INAUDIBLE]
SPEAKER 1: $40, will go with 4,000.
And what was your answer?
STAFF: We picked Kansas.
SPEAKER 1: Kansas, interesting.
Now, students, how much did you wager?
STUDENT: 2,000.
SPEAKER 1: 2,000.
and what was your answer?
STUDENT: Also Kansas.
SPEAKER 1: And also Kansas.
So 2,000 would bring you to 8,200.
4,000 would bring you to 8,000.
So if you're both right, students
you might have clinched it.
Does the audience remember
where Google thought
we were a few weeks ago,
despite the fact that I
misstated where Google thinks we were?
Oklahoma was my incorrect
answer, it turns out.
Wyoming, also incorrect.
But we can do sort of
binary search in that area.
Anyone at all?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
SPEAKER 1: It is, in fact, Kansas.
So congratulations to
the students' team.
A round of applause, if we
could, for our students.
Thank you so much for
joining us in CS50.
We are so proud of you all, cannot
wait to see you at the fair.
Cake is now served downstairs.
And my thanks again to the staff.