The human side of AI,
how do we turn this camera
back in on the human,
we are talking about perception,
how to detect cats and dogs,
pedestrians lanes,
how to steer a vehicle based on the
external environment,
the thing that's really fascinating and
severely understudied,
is the human side,
we talked about the Tesla,
we have cameras in 17 Tesla's
driving around Cambridge
because Tesla is one of the only vehicles
allowing you
to experience in a real way, on the road,
the interaction between the human
and the Machine,
the thing that we don't have,
that deep learning needs
on the human side of
semi-autonomous vehicles
and fully-autonomous vehicles
is video of drivers,
that's what we're collecting,
that's what my work is in,
is looking at billions
of video frames,
of human beings driving
60 miles an hour plus
on the highway
in their semi-autonomous Tesla,
what are the things that we want
to know about the human?
If we were a deep learning therapist,
we’d try to break apart
the different things we can detect
from this raw set of pixels,
we can look here,
from the green to red
is a different detection problem,
a different computer vision
detection problem
green means it's less challenging,
it's feasible,
even under poor lighting conditions,
variable pose, noisy environment,
poor resolution,
red means it's really hard
no matter what you do,
that's starting on the left
with face detection body pose,
one of the best studied
and one of the easier
computer vision problems,
we have huge datasets for these,
then there is micro saccades,
the slight tremors of the eye
that happen at a rate of
a thousand times a second.
All right let's look at—
First, why do we even care
about the human in the car?
One is trust, this trust part is a—
If you think about it,
to build trust
the car needs to have
some awareness of
the biological thing
it's carrying inside,
the human inside,
you assume the car
knows about you,
because you're sitting there
controlling it,
but if you think about it,
almost every single car
on the road today,
has no sensors
with which it's perceiving you,
it knows, some cars
have a pressure sensor
on the steering wheel
and a pressure sensor
or some kind of sensor
detecting that you're sitting
in the seat,
that's the only thing
it knows about you,
that's it,
so how is the car supposed to—
this same car
is driving 70 miles an hour,
on the highway, autonomously,
how is it supposed
to build trust with you
if it doesn't perceive you?
That's one of the
critical things here,
so if I'm constantly
advocating something,
is that we should have
a driver facing camera
in every car,
despite the privacy concerns,
you have a camera on your phone
and you don't have as much
of a privacy concern there,
but despite the privacy concerns,
the safety benefits are huge,
the trust benefits are huge.
Let's start with the easy one,
detecting body pose,
why do we care?
There is a seatbelt design,
there are these dummies,
crash-test dummies,
which we can use
to design the passive
safety systems of our cars,
and they make certain assumptions
about body shapes,
male, female, child, body shapes,
but they also make assumptions
about the position of
your body in the seat,
they have the optimal position,
the position they assume you take,
the reality is, in a Tesla,
when the car is driving itself,
the variability, if you remember
the deformable [unintelligible 00:04:44]
you start doing a little bit more
of that, you start to
reach back in the back seat,
in your purse, your bag,
for your cell phone,
these kinds of things,
that's when the crashes happen,
we to know how often that happens,
the car needs to know
that you're in that position,
that's critical for that
very serious moment
when the actual crash happens,
how do you do?
This is deep learning class,
this is deep learning to the rescue,
whenever you have
these kinds of tasks,
of detecting for example
body poses,
you're detecting points of the shoulders,
points of the head,
five-ten points along the arms,
the skeleton.
How do you do that?
You have a CNN,
convolutional neural network,
that takes its input image
and takes an output,
it's a regressor,
it gives an XY position
of whatever you're looking for,
the left shoulder, right shoulder,
then you have a cascade
of regressors
they give you all of these points,
they give you the shoulders,
the arms and so on,
then you have—
through time on
every single frame
you make that prediction
and then you optimize,
you can make certain
assumptions about physics,
your arm can't be in this place in one frame
and then the next frame
be over here,
it moves smoothly
through space
so under those constraints
you can then minimize the error--
the temporal error
from frame to frame
or you can just dump all the frames,
as if there are different channels
like RGB is three channels,
you can think of those channels
as in time,
you can dump
all those frames together,
and that's what I call
3D convolutional neural networks,
you've dumped them all together
and then you estimate
the body pose
in all the frames at once.
There are some data sets
for sports
and we're building our own—
I don't know who that guy is—
Let's fly through this a little bit,
so what's called gaze classification,
gaze is another word for glance,
it's a classification problem,
here's one of the TAs for this class,
Not here because he's married,
he had to be home,
I know were his priorities are at,
this is on camera,
he should be here,
[chuckles]
There's five cameras,
this is why we're recording in the Tesla.
This is a Tesla vehicle,
in the bottom right,
there's a blue icon
that lights up automatically detected
if it's operating under autopilot,
that means the car is currently
driving itself,
there's five cameras
one on the forward roadway,
one on the instrument cluster,
one on the center stack,
steering wheel,
his face,
then it's a classification problem,
you dump the raw pixels
into a convolutional neural network,
have six classes forward roadway,
you're predicting
where the person is looking,
forward roadway, left, right,
center stack, instrument cluster,
rearview mirror,
and you give millions of frames
for every class, simple.
And It does incredibly well at predicting
where the driver is looking,
the process is the same for majority
of the driver state problems
that have to do with the face,
the face has so much information,
where are you looking, emotion,
drowsiness,
different degrees of frustration,
I'll fly through those as well,
but the process is the same,
there's some pre-processing,
this is in the wild data,
there's a lot of crazy light going on,
there's noises,
vibration from the vehicle,
so first you have to—
video stabilization
you have to remove all that vibration,
all that noise, as best as you can,
there's a lot of algorithms,
non-neural network algorithms,
boring but they work
for removing the noise,
removing the effects of
sudden light variations and
vibrations of the vehicle,
there's the automated calibration,
so you have to estimate
the frame of the camera,
the position of the camera,
and estimate the identity
of the person you're looking at.
The more you can specialize the network
to the identity of the person
and the identity of the car
the person is riding in,
the better the performance for the
different driver state classification.
So you personalize the network,
you have a background model
that works on everyorne
and you specialize each individual,
this is transfer learning,
you specialize each individual network
to that one individual.
There is a face frontalization,
fancy name for the fact that
no matter where they're looking,
you want to transfer that face
so the eyes,
nose are the exact same position
in the image,
that way if you want to look at the eyes
and you want to study the subtle
movement of the eyes
the subtle blinking,
the dynamics of the eyelid,
the velocity of the eyelid,
it's always in the same place
so you can really focus in
remove all effects
of any other motion of the head,
and then you just—
it's the beauty of deep learning,
there is some pre-processing,
because this is real-world data,
but you just dump the raw pixels in,
you dump the raw pixels in and
predict whatever you need.
What do you need?
One is emotion, You can have—
I had a study where people
used a crappy and a good voice
based navigation system,
so the crappy one
got them really frustrated,
and they self-reported it
as the frustrating experience or not
on scale one to 10,
that gives us ground truth,
a bunch of people to used this system,
they put themselves as
frustrated or not,
so then we can predict,
we can train a Convolutional
neural network to predict
is this person frustrated or not,
I think we've seen a video of that,
turns out smiling is a strong
indication of frustration,
you can also predict
drowsiness in this way,
gaze estimation in this way,
cognitive load,
I'll briefly look at that,
the process is all the same,
you detect the face, you find the
landmark points in the face,
for the face alignment,
face frontalization,
and then you dump the raw pixels in
for classification, step five.
You can use SVM's there
or you can use what
everyone uses now,
convolutional neural networks.
This is the one part where CNN's
still struggle to compete,
is the alignment problem,
this is why I talked about
the Cascade regressors,
is finding the landmarks
on the eyebrows, the nose,
the jawline, the mouth,
there are certain constraints there,
so algorithms that can utilize those
constraints effectively
can often perform better than
end-to-end regressors
that just don't have any concept
of what a face is shaped like.
There are huge data sets
and we're a part
of the awesome community
that's building those data sets
for face alignment.
This is the TA in its younger form,
this is live in the car,
the real time system predicting
where they're looking,
this is taking slow steps
towards the exciting direction
that machine learning is headed,
which is unsupervised learning,
the less you have
to have humans look to the data
and annotate that data,
the more power these machine
learning algorithms get,
currently supervised learning
is what's needed,
you need human beings to label
a cat and label a dog,
if you can only have a
human being label 1%,
one tenth of a percent
of a data set, only the hard cases,
so the machine can come
to the human and be like,
I don't know what I'm
looking at in these pictures,
because of the partial
light occlusions,
we're not good
at dealing with occlusions,
whether it's your own arm
or because of light conditions,
we're not good with
crazy light
drowning out the image,
this is what Google self-driving cars
struggle with
when they're trying
to use their vision sensors,
moving out of frame,
all kinds of occlusion They are really hard
for computer vision algorithms,
and in those cases we want a machine
to step in and say--
and pass that image on to the human,
be like "help me out with this"
and the other corner case is,
in driving for example
90 plus percent of the time
all you're doing is
staring forward at the roadway
the same way,
that's where the Machine shines,
that's where machine automated
annotation shines,
because it's seen that face
for hundreds of millions
of frames already,
in that exact position,
so it can do all the hard work
of annotation for you,
it's in the transition away from those positions
that it needs a little bit of help,
just to make sure that this person
just started looking away
from the road to the rear view,
and you bring those points up,
so you're-- there's a—
using optical flow,
putting the optical flow
in the convolutional neural network,
you use that to predict
when something has changed
when something has changed you bring
that to the machine for annotation
all of this is to build a giant—
Billions of frames annotated data set,
our ground truth,
on which you train your
driver state algorithms,
in this way you can control,
on the x-axis
is the fraction of frames
the human has to annotate,
zero percent on the Left,
ten percent on the right,
and then the accuracy trade-off,
the more the human annotates,
the higher the accuracy,
you approach 100% accuracy,
but you can still do pretty good,
this is for the gaze classification task,
With an 84-- 84 fold to almost towards
the magnitude reduction
in human annotation,
this is the future
of machine learning,
and hopefully one day
no human annotation,
and the result is millions of images
like these video frames,
same thing, driver frustration,
this is what I was talking about,
the frustrated driver
is the one that's on the bottom,
so a lot of movement
of the eyebrows
and a lot of smiling, and that's
true subject after the subject,
And they're Happy, the satisfied,
I don't want to say happy,
the satisfied driver is
cold and stoic,
and that's true for
subject after subject,
because driving is a boring experience
and you want it to stay that way
Yes, question.
Great, great question,
they're not--
Absolutely, that's a great question
So these cars owned by MIT,
there is somebody in the back—
The comment was—
my emotions then have nothing to
do with the driving experience.
Yes, let me continue that comment,
your emotions are often—
You're an actor on the stage
for others with your emotion,
when you're alone,
you might not express emotion,
you're really expressing emotion
oftentimes for others,
your frustration is like
"What the heck"
that's for the passenger,
and that's absolutely right,
so one of the cool things
we're doing—
As I said, we now have over a billion
video frames in the Tesla,
We're starting to collected huge
amounts of data in the Tesla,
emotion is a complex thing,
in this case,
we know the ground truth,
how frustrated they were,
in naturalistic data, when it's just
people driving around,
we don't know how they're
really feeling at the moment,
we're not asking to enter an app
"how are you feeling right now?"
but we do know certain things,
we know that people sing a lot,
that has to be on paper
at some point,
it's awesome,
people love singing,
so that doesn't happen
in this kind of data,
because there's somebody
singing in the car,
and I think the expression
of frustration is also the same.
Yes. The question is—
or the comment is that
the solo data set is probably
going to be very different
from a data set that's not solo, with a passenger,
that's very true,
the tricky thing about driving
this is why it's a huge challenge
for self-driving cars
for the external facing sensors
and for the internal facing sensors
analyzing human behavior,
is 99.9% of driving is the same thing,
it's really boring.
So finding the interesting bits
is actually pretty complicated,
so that has to do with emotion,
that has to do with—
so singing is easy to find,
we can track the mouth pretty well,
so when you're talking of singing
we can find that,
but how do you find
the subtle expressions of emotion?
It's hard, when you're solo.
Cognitive load,
that's a fascinating thing,
I mean, similar emotion
it's a little more concrete
in a sense that there's good science
and ways to measure cognitive load,
cognitive workload,
how occupied your mind is,
mental workload
is another term used,
the window to the soul,
the cognitive workload soul
is the eyes,
so pupil—
first of all the eyes move in
two different ways
they move in a lot of ways but
two major ways is saccades,
these are these ballistic movements,
they jump around whenever
you look around the room,
they're actually just jumping around,
when you read
the eyes are jumping around,
Like if all of you just follow
this bottle with your eyes,
your eyes are actually going
to move smoothly,
a smooth pursuit.
Somebody actually told me today,
that probably has to do with our
hunting background as animals,
I don't know how that helps,
like frogs track flies really well,
so you have to like—
Anyway, the point is
there are smooth pursuit movements
where the eyes move smoothly,
and those are all indications
of certain aspects of cognitive load,
and then there are
these very subtle movements,
which are almost imperceptible
for computer vision
and these are micro saccades,
these are tremors of the eye,
a work from here,
from Bill Freeman,
magnifying those subtle movements,
these are taken at 500 frames a second.
So cognitive load—
when the pupil,
that black dot in the middle,
in case you don't know what a pupil is,
in the middle of the eye,
when it gets larger that's an indicative
of high cognitive load,
but it also gets larger
when the light is dim.
So there's this complex interplay,
so we can't rely in the wild outside,
in the car, or just in general outdoors,
using the pupil size,
even though pupil size
has been used effectively
in a lab to measure cognitive load,
it can't be reliably used in the car,
the same with blinks,
when there's a high cognitive load,
your blink rate decreases
and your blink duration shortens,
I think I'm just repeating
the same thing over and over,
but you can imagine
how we can predict cognitive load,
We extract a video of the eye.
Here is the primary eye of the person
the system is observing,
happens to be the same TA once again.
We take the sequence of 100--
it's 90 images, that's six seconds,
16 frames a second,
15 frames a second,
we dump that into a 3D
convolutional neural network,
that means it's 90 channels,
it's 90 frames, grayscale,
and then the prediction is one of
three classes of cognitive load,
low cognitive load, medium cognitive
load and high cognitive load,
there's ground truth for that,
because we have people--
over 500 different people
do different tasks
of various cognitive load,
and after some frontalization again,
where you see the eyes are traced
no matter where the person looking,
the image of the face is
transposed in such a way that
the corner of the eyes remain
always in the same position,
after the frontalization,
we find the eye,
active appearance models,
find 39 points of the eyelids, the iris,
and four points on the pupil.
Putting all of that into a 3D CNN model,
they're positioned,eye sequence on the left,
3D CNN model in the middle,
cognitive load prediction
on the right.
This code by the way
is freely available online.
All you have to do,
dump a web-cam
from the video stream,
CNN runs faster than real-time,
predicts cognitive load.
Same process as detecting
the identity of the face,
same process as detecting where
the driver is looking,
same process as detecting emotion
and all of those
require very little
hyper parameter tuning on
the convolutional neural networks,
they only require
huge amounts of data.
Why do we care about detecting
what the drivers doing?
I think Eric has mentioned this is--
On the-- Oh man, this is the comeback of the slide,
[laughter]
I was criticized for this being
a very cheesy slide,
in the past towards full automation,
we're likely to take
gradual steps towards that.
I can't, it's enough of that,
this is better—
Especially given that—
This is given today,
our new president,
this is a pickup truck country,
this is a manually
controlled vehicle country,
for quite a little while,
we like control
and control being given
to somebody else,
to the machine,
will be a gradual process,
it's a gradual process of that
machine earning trust,
and through that process,
the machine,
like the Tesla, like the BMW,
like the Mercedes, the Volvo,
that's now playing with these ideas,
it's going to need to see
what the human is doing,
and for that, to see what
the human is doing,
we have billions of miles of
forward-facing data, what we need,
is billions of miles of
driver facing data as well.
We're in the process of
collecting that,
this is a pitch for automakers
and everybody to buy cars
that have a driver facing camera.
And let me close--
I said we need a lot of data but
I think this class has been—
through your own research you'll find
that we're in the very early stages
of discovering the power
of deep learning,
for example, recently,
Jean [?] said
that it seems that
the deeper the network,
the better the results
in a lot of really important cases,
even though the data
is not increasing,
why does the deeper network
give better results?
This is a mysterious thing
we don't understand,
there's these hundreds of millions
of parameters,
from them is emerging
some kind of structure,
some kind of representation of the
knowledge that we're giving it.
One of my favorite examples
of this emergent concept
is the Conway's Game of Life.
For those of you who
knows what this is,
will probably criticize me
for being as cheesy
as the stairway slide,
but I think it's such a simple
and brilliant example
of how--
Like a neuron in a neural network
is a really simple computational unit,
and then incredible power emerges
when you combine a lot of them
in a network,
in the same way,
this is called
the cellular automata,
that's a weird pronunciation,
every single cells is operating
under a simple rule,
you can think of it as
a cell living and dying,
it's filled in black when it's alive
and white when it's dead,
if it's alive
and it has two or three neighbors,
it survives to the next time,
otherwise it dies,
and if it has exactly three neighbors,
and it's dead,
it comes back to life,
if it has exactly three neighbors,
that's a simple rule,
whatever,
you can just imagine,
it's just simple—
All is doing, is operating under
this very local process,
same as a neuron.
It's a—
or in the way
we're currently training
neural networks
and there's this local gradient,
we're optimizing over a local gradient,
the same local rules,
and what happens
if you run this system,
operating under really local rules,
what you get on the right,
it's not—
Again, you have to go home,
hopefully no drugs involved,
but you have to open up your mind
[chuckles]
and see how amazing that is,
because what happens is,
it's a local computational unit,
that knows very little
about the world,
but somehow really
complex patterns emerge
and we don't understand why,
in fact under different rules,
incredible patterns emerge,
and it feels like
it's living creatures communicating,
when you just watch it,
not these examples,
this is the original,
they get complex and interesting,
but even in these examples,
these complex geometric
patterns that emerge,
it's incredible,
we don't understand why,
same with neural networks,
and we need to in order to see how
these networks will be able to reason.
What's next?
I encourage you to read
the deep learning book,
it's available online,
deeplearningbook.org.
As I mentioned to a few people,
you should--
Well, first there's a ton
of amazing papers
every day coming out on archive,
I'll put these links up,
but there's a lot of good
collections of strong papers,
lists of papers, there is
the literally awesome list,
the awesome deep learning
papers on GitHub,
it's calling itself awesome,
but it happens to be awesome,
there is a lot of blogs,
it's just amazing,
that's how I recommend you
learn machine learning,
on blogs,
and if you're interested
in the application of deep learning
in the automotive space,
you can come and do
research in our group,
just email me.
Anyway, we have three winners,
Jeffrey Hu, Michael Gump
how  do you-- Are you here?
How do you say your name?
No, that's not my name
[laughter]
My name is Purna [?]
Oh, I see.
[?]
Well, anyway here--
[applause]
He achieved the stunning speed of--
So this is kind of incredible,
I didn't know
what kind of speed
we were going to be able to achieve,
I thought 73 was unbeatable,
because we played with it
for a while
and we couldn't achieve 73,
we design a deterministic algorithm
that was able to achieve 74
I believe,
meaning like it's cheating,
with the cheating algorithm
that got 74,
folks have come up
with algorithms that have done—
that had beaten 73
and then 74,
so this is really incredible,
and the other two guys—
all three of you
get a free term at the Udacity
self-driving car engineering degree,
Thanks to those guys
for giving that award
and bringing their army of brilliant—
So they have people
who are obsessed about
self-driving cars,
and we've received
over 2,000 submissions
for this competition,
a lot of them from those guys,
they're just brilliant,
it's really exciting to have
such a big community
of deep learning folks
working in this field,
this is for the rest of eternity,
we're going to
change this up a little bit,
but this is actually
the three neural networks,
the three winning neural networks
running side by side,
you can see
the number of cars passed there,
the first place is on the left,
second place, and third place,
and in fact,
the third place it's almost--
right now, second place
is winning currently,
but that just tells you
the random nature of competition,
sometimes you win,
sometimes loose.
The actual evaluation process
runs through a lot of iterations
and takes the medium evaluation.
With that, let me thank you
guys so much for—
Wait, we have a question—
are the winning networks online?
Yes.
All three guys
wrote me a note
about how their networks work,
I did not read that note,
[chuckles]
I'll post—This tells you how
crazy this has been,
I'll post the winning networks online,
and I encourage you to
continue competing
and continue submitting networks.
This will run for a while we're
working on a journal paper
for this game.
We're trying to find the
optimal solutions.
Okay. This is the first time
I've ever taught a class,
and the first time obviously
teaching this class,
so thank you so much
for being a part of it.
[Applause]
Thank you to Eric,
if you didn't get a shirt
please come back,
please come down and get a shirt,
just write your email on the note,
on the on the index note.
Thank you.